<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the old governors of the free grammar-school in Birmingham in the county of Warwick, appellants against a decree made in the Court of Chancery in the name of the attorney-general, at the relation of the new governors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1119A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173474</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">61296903</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 61296903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2831:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the old governors of the free grammar-school in Birmingham in the county of Warwick, appellants against a decree made in the Court of Chancery in the name of the attorney-general, at the relation of the new governors.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Schools --  England --  Birmingham --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Birmingham (England) --  History --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF THE Old Governors <hi>of the</hi> FREE GRAMMAR-SCHOOL <hi>in</hi> BIRMINGHAM <hi>in the County of</hi> WARWICK, Appellants, <hi>againſt a</hi> DECREE <hi>made in the</hi> Court of CHANCERY, <hi>in the Name of the</hi> Attorney-General, <hi>at the Relation of the</hi> New Governors.</head>
            <p>KIng <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Die Januanriei Anno <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> by his Letters-Patents of that Date, erected a Free Grammar-School in <hi>Birmingham</hi> aforeſaid, for the Benefit of the ſaid Town, and thereby appointed Twenty of the moſt diſcreet Inhabitants of the ſame Town, to be Governors of the ſame School; whom he did thereby Incorporate: And by the ſame Letters-Patents granted to them and their Succeſſors Lands to the Value of One and twenty Pounds <hi>per An.</hi> for the Support of the ſaid School: And gave them Power to Elect a School-maſter and Uſher, and New Governors, as often as any of the Old ſhould die or leave the ſaid Town, (ſpecial Proviſion being made by the ſaid Letters-Patents, <hi>That none but the Reſiding Inhabitants of that Town ſhould be capable of the Government.</hi>) And further, by the ſaid Letters-Patents it was provided, That the Governors, by the Conſent of the Lord Biſhop of the Dioceſs for the time being, ſhould have Power to make Orders as well for the Government of the ſaid School, as for the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Rents ariſing out of the ſaid Lands.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſſive Governors of the ſaid School, ever ſince the Foundation thereof, having taken great care to chuſe able School-maſters ſucceſſively to that Place, and having by their Induſtry and Prudence improved the Rents of the ſaid Lands, by Building and otherwiſe, from One and twenty Pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> to about Three hundred Pounds a Year; by means whereof this School has for ſeveral Years laſt paſt been a great Nurſery of Learning, and thereby a Publick Advantage to the Kingdom, which have been in a great meaſure occaſioned by the Encouragement ſome poor Scholars of that School received from the ſaid Governors, out of the improved Rents, by the Conſent of the Biſhop of the ſaid Dioceſs, towards their Maintenance at the Univerſity.</p>
            <p>Which Methods continued until the latter end of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, at which time the then Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries Letter was brought by a Neighbouring Gentleman of that Country, directed to the Governors, purporting, That King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second required a Surrender of their <hi>Charter;</hi> to which if they complied, the Bearer told them, they might continue Governors, and have a new <hi>Charter,</hi> with greater and more ample Priviledges: But upon refuſal, he alſo told them what a ſevere Proſecution they muſt expect from his then Majeſty; And at the ſame inſtant prevailed with ſome of the moſt unwary Governors to joyn in an Inſtrument for the Surrender of their <hi>Charter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Surrender was never Inrolled: But after King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Death, in the Firſt Year of King <hi>James</hi> the Second, a New <hi>Charter</hi> was granted, wherein the Perſon that brought the ſaid Letter, and thereby procured the ſaid Surrender, is made a Governor, together with ſeveral other Perſons of his Acquaintance, inhabiting far diſtant from the ſaid Town, and in other Counties, and not above Five of the ſaid Governors therein named are inhabiting within the Town: In which laſt-granted <hi>Charter</hi> the King reſerved a Power to himſelf of Removing or Diſplacing any of the ſaid Governors and Maſters of the ſaid School at his Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Upon this, the Old School-maſter is removed, although he had for many Years together acquitted himſelf in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner in that Employment, and greatly to the ſatisfaction of the Inhabitants, for whoſe Benefit the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was deſigned, and a New Maſter brought thither in his room, againſt the Good-will and Inclination of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the ſaid Town, whereby their Children are neglected, and the poor Scholars are totally deprived of their Subſiſtence and Exhibitions formerly received in the Univerſity.</p>
            <p>The Inconveniency of which New <hi>Charter</hi> was ſoon felt in another manner, it being totally in his then Majeſty's Power; and the Town having generally a great averſion to Popery, when not one Inch of Ground could be procured in that Place, from any of the Inhabitants, to build a Popiſh Chappel on, for the propagating that Religion, a long Leaſe is made of part of the School-Lands for that purpoſe, and a Chappel erected accordingly on the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus ſtood the ſtate of the School until Their preſent Majeſties (the Great Reſtorers of our Ancient Liberties and Privileges) happy Acceſſion to the Crown; at which time the ſaid Surrender not being Inrolled, your Petitioners, the Old Governors, were adviſed to, and did act as formerly; and being obſtructed by the New Governors, they brought their Ejectment at Law, and did recover therein; and thereupon the New Governors, immediately by Petition, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied themſelves to the then Lords Commiſſioners of the Great Seal, for liberty to Inroll the ſaid Surrender, but were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the ſame, upon hearing Counſel on both ſides: And thereupon the ſaid New Governors Petitioned the Houſe of Commons, for leave to bring in a Bill, to be paſſed into an Act of Parliament, for Settling the School upon the New Foundation; and the ſame was referred to a Committee: Who, upon an Examination thereof, reported to the Houſe, That they ſaw no Cauſe to bring in a Bill; and the ſame was thereon rejected.</p>
            <p>That the New Governors, who are the Reſpondents, having met with theſe Diſappointments, then exhibited their Bill in <hi>Chancery,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trin.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> in the Name of the Attorney-General, thereby praying the ſaid Surrender might be then Inrolled; which, upon the hearing of the Cauſe on the Tenth of <hi>July</hi> laſt, the Court ordered accordingly; and that the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid School be ſettled under the ſaid New <hi>Charter;</hi> and that the Governors thereby, and their Succeſſors, do quietly Hold and Exerciſe the ſaid Government, under the ſaid New <hi>Charter,</hi> and diſpoſe and order the Lands and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues thereto belonging, againſt the Old Governors, and all Claiming under them, ſince the Information Exhibited: And that an Injunction be Awarded, to prevent the Old Governors from Trying their Right at Law, notwithſtanding the ſaid Inrollment.</p>
            <p>From which Decree the Old Governors have Appealed to the Right Honourable the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> for the Reverſal thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180487:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
